## Md Rayed Bin Wahed

https://www.linkedin.com/in/rayedbw https://www.github.com/rayedbar Email: rayed.bin.wahed@g.bracu.ac.bd Mobile: +880 1774-882517

Address: Uttara, Dhaka 1230, Bangladesh

Software engineer with substantial experience in developing SaaS applications and machine learning. An ambitious yet pragmatic team leader with a track record of implementing novel ideas. Humble and cheerful, a firm believer in using technology for a more equitable, ethical, and greener society.

#### Work Experience

## • Therap (BD) Ltd.

Team Lead, Machine Learning

Dhaka, Bangladesh Oct 2019 - Present

Therap (BD) Ltd. is a wholly-owned subsidiary of Therap Services LLC., USA. Therap is a web-based application suite designed to provide a comprehensive solution for the planning, documentation, reporting, and billing needs of organizations supporting people with Intellectual and Developmental Disabilities (IDD).

- Pulse Oximetry: Implemented a system to track blood oxygen saturation (SpO2) and heart rate of IDD individuals as an early detection mechanism for COVID-19. Saved the lives of 2 individuals so far.
- Optical Character Recognition: Leveraged OCR to extract SpO2 and heart-rate measurements from images of pulse oximeters. Eradicated false data entry.
- Customer Retention: Trained a classification model to predict the quarterly status of Therap customers. Developed a feature recommender system to facilitate greater discovery of services. Increased retention rate by 10%.
- Fall Detection: Implemented an RNN model to detect accidental falls from gyroscope and accelerometer data. The system improved caregivers responsiveness by 80%.
- Face Recognition: Implemented a face recognition model to identify and track unauthorized individuals from a live video feed. Improved on-premise security. The model had an accuracy of 97%.
- Sleep Analysis: Utilized sensor readings from sleep mats, smartwatches, and smart-rings to implement comprehensive sleep profiles (sleep state diagrams, bed in/out statistics) of individuals. The intention was to inform caregivers of the quality of sleep the individuals.
- Related Technologies: Python, TensorFlow 2.0, Scikit-Learn, PyTorch, Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly, Docker, Jupyter Notebooks, React, GraphQL, AWS Amplify.

#### • Therap (BD) Ltd.

Full Stack Software Engineer

Dhaka, Bangladesh Oct 2016 - Sep 2019

- Back-end: Worked closely with engineering teams to understand product requirements, draw up design specifications, and implement core application features in Java using Spring MVC and Hibernate ORM.
- **Front-end**: Implemented interactive UI components in JavaScript. Reduced code clutter and improved site responsiveness by 20%.
- Database: 3+ years of experience with Oracle Database and MySQL. Wrote PL/SQL to migrate large volumes of data. Implemented indices for faster queries and optimization.
- **Deployment**: Extensive experience deploying applications in Oracle Weblogic Server. Used Gradle to build applications and manage dependencies.
- $\circ$  **API**: Proficient in implementing and consuming REST and GraphQL APIs. Considerable experience developing serverless applications using frontend libraries like React.
- o Related Technologies: Node, Flask, Docker, NoSQL IntelliJ IDEA.

#### PROJECTS

#### • We Are X

Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan 2019 - Mar 2019

Machine Learning Consultant (Contractual, Remote)

Online social-media customer service platform for large enterprises.

- Task: Implemented a text classification model to classify customer queries written in Bengali and English. Achieved 90% accuracy working on a limited dataset.
- Outcome: Improved customer service representative productivity by 30% allowing We Are X to meet market demand keeping existing infrastructure intact.

#### • Machine Learning Nanodegree

Udacitu

Dhaka, Bangladesh Nov 2019 - Jan 2020

- o Certificate earned on January 30, 2020: Link to Certificate.
- **Project**: Implemented a Human Activity Recognition (HAR) LSTM deep learning model using WISDM Smartphone and Smartwatch Activity and Biometrics Dataset. Obtained an accuracy of 90% using just the smartwatch data.

### • Machine Learning with TensorFlow on Google Cloud Platform Specialization

Google Cloud Authorized Online Training

- End-to-End Machine Learning with TensorFlow on GCP by Google Cloud on Coursera. Certificate earned at Saturday, January 12, 2019 4:58 AM GMT: Link to Certificate.
- Intro to TensorFlow by Google Cloud on Coursera. Certificate earned at Thursday, January 3, 2019 5:01 PM GMT: Link to Certificate.

#### • Deep Learning Specialization

Online Courses Taught by Professor Andrew Ng of Stanford University

- Deep Learning, a 5-course specialization by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Specialization Certificate earned on April 9, 2018: Link to Certificate.
- Sequence Models by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Certificate earned at Monday, April 9, 2018 1:34 AM GMT: Link to Certificate.
- Convolutional Neural Networks by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Certificate earned at Saturday, March 10, 2018 4:36 PM GMT: Link to Certificate.
- Structuring Machine Learning Projects by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Certificate earned at Monday, January 22, 2018 12:32 PM GMT: Link to Certificate.
- Improving Deep Neural Networks: Hyperparameter tuning, Regularization and Optimization by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Certificate earned at Wednesday, January 17, 2018 5:16 PM GMT: Link to Certificate.
- Neural Networks and Deep Learning by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Certificate earned at Friday, January 12, 2018 5:45 AM GMT: Link to Certificate.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### • BRAC University

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science

Jan 2012 - Aug 2016

- High Distinction: Awarded High Distinction for a Cumulative Grade Point Average (CGPA) of 3.75/4.00.
- Merit Based Scholarship: Awarded Merit Based Scholarship for the duration of the entire program.
- **Teacher Assistant**: Worked part-time as a TA for courses Data Structures and Discrete Mathematics starting junior year.

#### AWARDS AND HONORS

#### • President's Volunteer Service Award

USA

President's Council on Service and Civic Participation

Aug 2008

• Recognition: Awarded President's Volunteer Service Award from the President's Council on Service and Civic Participation for outstanding service to community and country.

## • Youth Exchange and Study (YES) Program

Seattle, USA

Aspect Foundation

Aug 2007 - Sep 2008

• Recognition: One of twenty students from Bangladesh to successfully complete the US Department of State funded YES Program. A humbling experience that prides itself in leadership, cultural values, and acceptance.

# • International School Cricket Premier League *ISCPL*

Lucknow, India

Jan 2011

• Recognition: Represented Bangladesh as a cricketer in the first ever International School Cricket Premier League organized by City Montessori School & Degree College and sponsored by the International Cricket Council (ICC).